Atriya Sen

Postdoctoral Research Associate School of Life Sciences Arizona State University Tempe, Arizona, USA +1 (518) 308 5117 Atriya@AtriyaSen.com

PROFILE

Artificial intelligence researcher; skilled in computational logic, formal modeling / knowledge representation / ontological engineering of complex domains, machine reasoning & explainable / interpretable machine learning / data mining. I code in Python & Prolog.

WORK EXPERIENCE (RESEARCH)

- * Postdoctoral Research Associate, School of Life Sciences, Arizona State University 2019—current
 - On automated reasoning for the biological taxonomy alignment problem. Supervised by Prof. Nico Franz.
- Postdoctoral Research Associate, Rensselaer Artificial Intelligence & Reasoning Laboratory (https://rair.cogsci.rpi.edu), Department of Cognitive Science & Department of Computer Science, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute — 2018–2019
 - On *Tentacular AI*, a new theory of ethically and cognitively informed machine reasoning for the Internet of Things (IoT), a collaboration with IBM Research (funded by IBM & RPI under the AIRC program). Description available here: http://kryten.mm.rpi.edu/TAI/tai.html. Supervised by Prof. Selmer Bringsjord.
- * Assistant Director, Rensselaer Artificial Intelligence & Reasoning Laboratory (https://rair.cogsci.rpi.edu), Department of Cognitive Science & Department of Computer Science, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute 2015–2019
 - Supervised 3 undergraduate AI researchers in summer 2018 and 4 undergraduate AI researchers in summer 2016.
 - Co-authored successful proposal to the US Air Force Office of Scientific Research for 2-year grant (AF9550-12-1-0003) for computational reasoning in the natural sciences, economics, and mathematical logic.
- Intern, Cognitive Computing, IBM Research Zürich June–August 2017

- On chemical reaction prediction using symbolic machine learning (inductive logic programming), advised by Dr. Teodoro Laino.
- Research Assistant, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute 2013–2014
 - Funded by the US Naval Research Lab for machine reasoning in language education.
- Project-Linked Person (Research Assistant), Indian Statistical Institute 2011–2012
 - Computer Vision & Pattern Recognition Unit. Statistical machine learning to tune OCR software for the Bengali language.

WORK EXPERIENCE (TEACHING)

- * I am co-teaching (with Prof. Selmer Bringsjord) the course 'Are Humans Rational?', an investigation of the eponymous question, at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in the Fall 2018 semester.
- * Guest Lecturer, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute 2015-current
 - Guest lectures in 'Introduction to Logic' and 'Are Humans Rational?'
- * Teaching Assistant, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute 2012–2013, 2014–2015
 - Assisted with undergraduate programming and data structures courses, and (twice) CSCI 4150 'Introduction to Artificial Intelligence', a graduate-level course.

WORK EXPERIENCE (PROGRAMMING)

- * I program in Python & Prolog, and have programmed in C++, PHP, Lisps, and Oz.
- * Google Summer of Code 2012.
- * Associate Programmer, Indus Net Technologies, Kolkata 2010–2011
 - Worked closely with clients to develop enterprise web solutions in PHP (backend).

EDUCATION

- Doctor of Philosophy (Computer Science) Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, 2017; advised by Prof. Selmer Bringsjord.
 - Sen, A. (2017). Computational Axiomatic Science. *Ph.D. Dissertation, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute*.

- * Master of Computer Applications West Bengal University of Technology, Kolkata, India, 2010.
- * Bachelor of Science in Physics, with Honours (cum laude) St. Xavier's College, University of Calcutta, Kolkata, India, 2007.

CERTIFICATE

* Neural Networks and Deep Learning by deeplearning.ai on Coursera. Certificate available here: https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/S3SR5C2EJEJ7.

PUBLICATIONS AND CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS (PEER-REVIEWED)

- * G., Naveen S., Bringsjord, S., and Sen A. (2019). Towards Proof-Theoretic Semantics for the Deontic Cognitive Event Calculus. To be presented at the Workshop on Logic and Cognition, Indian Institute of Technology, New Delhi, India, 2019, held in conjunction with the Eighth Indian Conference on Logic and its Applications.
- * G., Naveen S., Paquin, J-C., Banerjee, S., Sen, A., Mayol, P. (2019). On Datasets for Evaluating Architectures for Learning to Reason. Forthcoming in the *Proceedings of the AAAI 2019 Spring Symposium on Combining Machine Learning with Knowledge Engineering (AAAI-MAKE 2019), Stanford University, Palo Alto, California, USA, 2019.*
- * Bringsjord, S., G., Naveen S., Sen, A., Peveler, M., Srivastava, B., Talamadupula, K. (2018). Tentacular Artificial Intelligence, and the Architecture Thereof, Introduced. In the Proceedings of the 1st International FAIM Workshop on Architectures and Evaluation for Generality, Autonomy & Progress in AI (AEGAP 2018), Stockholm, Sweden, 2018, held in conjunction with IJCAI-ECAI 2018, AAMAS 2018 and ICML 2018. Pre-print available here: http://kryten.mm.rpi.edu/TAI_AEGAP2018_cc.pdf.
- * Sen, A., G., Naveen S., Bringsjord, S., Ghosh, R., Mayol, P., Srivastava, B., Talamadupula, K. (2018). Toward a Smart City using Tentacular AI. In the *Proceedings of the 2018 European Conference on Ambient Intelligence, Larnaca, Cyprus, 2018, Lecture Notes in Computer Science (Springer LNCS), Vol. 11249.*
- * Peveler, M., G., Naveen S., Bringsjord, S., Sen, A. et al. Toward Cognitive-and-Immersive Systems: Experiments in a Cognitive Microworld. Forthcoming in the Proceedings of the 6th Annual Conference on Advances in Cognitive Systems, Stanford, CA, USA, 2018.
- * Bringsjord, S., Sen, A., G., Naveen S., Paquin, J-C. et al. (2018). Ethical Operating Systems. *Reflections on Programming Systems (Springer, Cham), Pages 235-260.*

- * Sen, A., Srivastava, B. et al. For AIs, Is it Ethically/Legally Permitted That Ethical Obligations Override Legal Ones? Forthcoming in the *Proceedings of the International Conference on Robot Ethics and Standards (ICRES 2018)*, Troy, NY, USA, 2018.
- * Bringsjord, S., G., Naveen S., and Sen, A. Demystifying "Value Alignment": Formally Linking Axiology to Ethical Principles in a Deontic Cognitive Calculus. Forthcoming in the *Proceedings of the International Conference on Robot Ethics and Standards (ICRES 2018), Troy, NY, USA*, 2018.
- * Bringsjord, S., Sen, A., and G., Naveen S. Non-Standard Analysis is a Counter-Example to the Enculturated Model of the Mind. At the *Workshop on Mathematics and Culture - II, Kolkata, India*, 2018.
- * Sen, A., G., Naveen S., and Bringsjord, S. A Relativistic Event Calculus. At the 3rd International Conference on Logic, Relativity and Beyond, Budapest, Hungary, 2017. Extended abstract available here: https://www.renyi.hu//conferences/lrb17/pdf/Sen--Sundar-Bringsjord.pdf.
- * G., Naveen S., Bringsjord, S., Ghosh, R., Sen, A. et al. A Study in Suicide via Defeasible Cognitive Calculi: With Provision for Self-Reasoning. At the 2017 Annual Meeting of the International Association for Computing and Philosophy, Stanford, CA, USA, 2017.
- * Sen, A., Peveler, M., Marton, N. et al. (2016). Toward the Cognitive Classroom: Mathematical Physics. At the 6th European Immersive Education Summit, Padua, Italy, 2016. Forthcoming in the Journal of Immersive Education, edited by Aaron E. Walsh.
- * Bringsjord, S. and Sen, A. (2016). On Creative Self-Driving Cars. *Applied Artificial Intelligence, Volume 30, Issue 8, Pages 758-786.* (Uncorrected) pre-print available here: http://kryten.mm.rpi.edu/SB AS CreativeSelf-DrivingCars 0323161130NY.pdf.
- * Bringsjord, S., Licato, J., Sen, A., Johnson, J., Bringsjord, A., and Taylor, J. (2015). On Logicist Agent-based Economics. In the *Proceedings of the 11th Artificial Economics Conference, Porto, Portugal (Porto, Portugal: University of Porto)*. Available here: http://kryten.mm.rpi.edu/SB_JL_AS_JJ_AB_NS_JT_AE2015_0605152315NY.pdf.
- * Bringsjord, S., Licato, J., G., Naveen S., Ghosh, R., and Sen, A. (2015). Real Robots That Pass Human Tests of Self-consciousness. In the *Proceedings of the 24th IEEE Symposium on Robots and Human Interactive Communications, Kobe, Japan (New York, NY: IEEE)*, Pages 498-504. Pre-print available here: http://kryten.mm.rpi.edu/SBringsjord_etal_self-con_robots_kg4_0601151615NY.pdf.
- * Sen, A., Bringsjord, S., Marton, N., and Licato, J. Toward Diagrammatic Automated Discovery in Axiomatic Physics. At the 2nd International Conference on Logic, Relativity and Beyond, Budapest, Hungary, 2015. Available here: https://www.renyi.hu//conferences/lrb15/LRB15 Sen--Bringsjord--Marton--Licato.pdf.

CONFERENCE & WORKSHOP ORGANIZATION & REVIEWING

- * Organizing Committee, International Workshop on Urban Intelligence 2019, London, UK.
- * Program Committee, Second AAAI Workshop on Reasoning and Learning for Human-Machine Dialogues (DEEP-DIAL 2019), Honolulu, HI, USA.
- * Organizing Committee, International Conference on Robot Ethics and Standards 2018 (ICRES 2018), Troy, NY, USA.
- * Reviewer, Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society 2014 (CogSci 2014).

BOOKS

- * Sen, A., Bringsjord, S., and G., Naveen S. Computational Axiomatic Science. *Forthcoming*.
- * Baase, S. and Sen, A. (2013). A Gift of Fire: Social, Legal, and Ethical Issues for Computing Technology (Boston: Pearson). Fourth International Edition.

CONFERENCE POSTERS

- * Bringsjord, S., G., Naveen S., Sen, A., and Elmore, C. (2019). A Formalization of Cognitive Continuity/Discontinuity, to Settle the Darwin's-Mistake Debate. At the 41st Annual Meeting of the Cognitive Science Society (CogSci 2019), Montreal, Canada.
- * Peveler, M. et al., & Sen, A. et al. (2017). Framework for Mental Models for the Cognitively Smart Immersive Room. At the September 2017 IBM Research Cognitive Colloquium, Yorktown Heights, NY, USA.
- * Sen, A., G., Naveen S., Bergland, E., Licato, J. et al. (2017). Computational Exploration of Gödel's Speedup Theorem. At the 5th Annual Conference on Advances in Cognitive Systems, Troy, NY, USA.
- * Bringsjord, S., Sen, A., Elmore, C., and G., Naveen S. (2017). Toward Formalizing the Darwin's-Mistake Debate. At the 5th Annual Conference on Advances in Cognitive Systems, Troy, NY, USA.
- * Peveler, M., Sen, A., G., Naveen S., and Bringsjord, S. (2017). Toward Plan Recognition that Incorporates Theory of Mind. At the 5th Annual Conference on Advances in Cognitive Systems, Troy, NY, USA.
- * Peveler, M., O'Neill, K., Sen, A. et al. (2016). The Planning Dilemma in Cognitive Computing. At the September 2016 IBM Research Cognitive Colloquium, Yorktown Heights, NY, USA.

- Sen, A., Peveler, M., Marton, N. et al. (2015). Toward the Cognitive Classroom: Mathematical Physics. At the November 2015 Rensselaer-IBM Research Cognitive Colloquium, Troy, NY, USA.
- * Sen, A. & Dana, S. K. (2009). A composite image encryption algorithm using a 3-order cellular neural network and the DES symmetric-key block cipher. At the *International Symposium on Complex Dynamical Systems and Applications, Digha, India.*

OTHER TALKS

- * G., Naveen S., Paquin, J-C., Banerjee, S., Sen, A., Bringsjord, S. (2018). On Evaluating Learning to Reason. Presented at the *IBM AI Week 2018 Knowledge Representation Meets Machine Learning Workshop, Cambridge, MA, USA, 2018*.
- * Computational Axiomatic Science. Invited talk at *IBM Research Boston & IBM Research Yorktown Heights*, 2017.
- * Toward Learning Chemical Reactivity. Invited talk at IBM Research Zürich, 2017.
- * 3 Minute Thesis Competition. Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, 2017.
- * Towards a More Cultured Computer. At the Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute School of Science Graduate Research Symposium 2014.
- * Scientific Computing with Python. Invited talk at the Software Freedom Day 2011, Indian Statistical Institute, Kolkata, India.

AWARDS

- * 3 Minute Thesis Competition. Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, 2017. Placed runner-up.
- * Bishop Cashmere Award for Outstanding Creative Talent. St. James' School, Kolkata, India, 2004.

CODA

* I play classical piano, co-edited a college science magazine, was on RPI's School of Science Council, have won awards at national-level debate moots, and chess tournaments.